A Guide to the Papers of Edwin A. Alderman
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series I: Correspondence
  - 1929-1930 Correspondence concerning Speeches and Articles by Alderman - "Relations Between the Church and State Institutions of Higher Training" delivered to the Presbyterian Church (Box-folder 9:3)
  - 1930-1931 Correspondence concerning Speeches and Articles by Alderman - the Tribute to Thomas Jefferson on the Radio (Box-folder 9:4)
  - 1904-1931 Correspondence concerning the University of Virginia, including: a meeting to be held to form a College Entrance Examination Board for the state of Virginia (December 9, 1904); changes to the Summer School (January 1, 1907); a site for a memorial to Robert E. Lee (February 12, 1907); the University as a state institution and its funding (February 26, 1907); fund-raising (November 13, 1908; February 6, 1909; March 11, 1909; February 26, 1917); report of the Educational Commission created under Virginia state House bill #177 (January 10, 1910); the Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching (January 13, 1910); report on the current condition of the Department of Medicine (November 21, 1910); the Women's College issue (February 29, 1912; March 6, 1920; February 27, 1922); Elmer Irving Carruthers (1874-1952), letter from Alderman appointing Carruthers as Bursar (June 14, 1912); religion, church membership and number of teetotalers at the University (January 12, 1922; March 1, 1923); Virginia Quarterly Review (July 21, 1924); Alderman's refusal to accept the chancellorship of the University of Georgia (November 14, 1925); proposal for a School of Social Sciences (February 3, March 10, 1927); a proposed new library (June 3, 12, 1929); report of Department of Building and Grounds (January 10, 1931); and distribution of the Peabody Fund (n.d.) (Box-folder 9:5)
  - 1924-1925 Correspondence concerning Woodrow Wilson resulting from Alderman's requests of various persons to give their judgment of Wilson which he initiated before his speech about Wilson, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent - A through D, including: Lawrence Fraser Abbott, Stockton Axson, Newton Diehl Baker, Ray Stannard Baker, Bernard Mannes Baruch, Dr. Hugh Black, Union Theological Seminary, Tasker Howard Bliss, John Gutzon de las Mothe Borglum, Gamaliel Bradford, Louis Dembitz Brandeis, Robert Bridges, Eugene Clyde Brooks, Bainbridge Colby, Archibald Cary Coolidge, George Creel, Homer Stille Cummings, John William Davis, William Edward Dodd, and Cleveland Hoadley Dodge (Box-folder 9:6)
  - 1924-1925 Correspondence concerning Woodrow Wilson resulting from Alderman's requests of various persons to give their judgment of Wilson which he initiated before his speech about Wilson, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent - E through M, including: Charles William Eliot, Henry Burchard Fine, John Huston Finley, Harry Emerson Fosdick, Harry Augustus Garfield, Cary Travers Grayson, Thomas Watt Gregory, Arthur Twining Hadley, Norman Hapgood, William Hard, Florence Harriman, Archibald Henderson, Gilbert Monell Hitchcock, Edward Mandell House, Herbert Sherman Houston, John Holladay Latane, William Gibbs McAdoo, Vance Criswell McCormick, William Fraser McDowell, Thomas Riley Marshall, Edward Sanford Martin, Alexander Meiklejohn, Edwin Mims, Samuel Chiles Mitchell, and Robert Walton Moore (Box-folder 9:7)
  - 1924-1925 Correspondence concerning Woodrow Wilson resulting from Alderman's requests of various persons to give their judgment of Wilson which he initiated before his speech about Wilson, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent - N through W, including: Joseph Fort Newton, John Barton Payne, George Foster Peabody, Frank Lyon Polk, Roscoe Pound, Lindsay Rogers, Albert Shaw, Swagar Sherley, Kenneth Charles Morton Sills, Claude Augustus Swanson, Ida Minerva Tarbell, James Henry Taylor, Joseph Patrick Tumulty, Henry Van Dyke, William Allen White, and John Sharp Williams (Box-folder 10:1)
  - 1924-1925 Correspondence concerning Woodrow Wilson Speech given by Alderman delivered before Congress and printed in the Congressional Record, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent - A through B (Box-folder 10:2)
  - 1924-1925 Correspondence concerning Woodrow Wilson Speech given by Alderman delivered before Congress and printed in the Congressional Record, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent - C through F (Box-folder 10:3)
  - 1924-1925 Correspondence concerning Woodrow Wilson Speech given by Alderman delivered before Congress and printed in the Congressional Record, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent - G through J (Box-folder 10:4)
  - 1924-1925 Correspondence concerning Woodrow Wilson Speech given by Alderman delivered before Congress and printed in the Congressional Record, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent - K through Ma (Box-folder 10:5)
  - 1924-1925 Correspondence concerning Woodrow Wilson Speech given by Alderman delivered before Congress and printed in the Congressional Record, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent - Me through R (Box-folder 10:6)
  - 1924-1925 Correspondence concerning Woodrow Wilson Speech given by Alderman delivered before Congress and printed in the Congressional Record, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent - S through V (Box-folder 10:7)
  - 1924-1925 Correspondence concerning Woodrow Wilson Speech given by Alderman delivered before Congress and printed in the Congressional Record, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent - W through Z (Box-folder 11:1)
  - 1924-1925 Correspondence concerning the Woodrow Wilson Memorial Address Publication, including the Memorandum of Agreement (Box-folder 11:2)
- Series II: Topical Files
  - 1888, n.d. Address Books belonging to Edwin A. Alderman, one chiefly concerning London and Paris addresses and accounts (Box-folder 11:3)
  - 1936-1937 Alderman Alumni Fund Literature (Box-folder 11:4)
  - 1863, 1865, n.d. Alderman Family Papers, includes: a receipt for the purchase by George and James Alderman of a Negro slave named Paro, from Isabella C. McCall, for eleven hundred and five dollars, Wilmington, North Carolina; General Orders No. 4, April 11, 1865, issued by Camp Headquarters, 7 th Regiment North Carolina Home Guard, to Lt. James Alderman and Captain A.E. Hall, Company A, relieving the regiment of further duty by the Governor of the state; a mostly blank form appointing N.M Osborne as an attorney to subscribe in the Capital Stock of the Atlantic, Mississippi & Ohio Rail Road Company by surrender of stock in the Virginia & Tennessee Rail Road Company, 1872; autograph of General Ulysses S. Grant, n.d. (original transferred to the Vault - Autograph Collection); typescript of a letter from Thomas B. Macaulay to Randall, [May 23, 1857], as to why Macaulay did not have a high opinion of Thomas Jefferson nor reckoned him among the benefactors of mankind (n.d.) (Box-folder 11:5)
  - 1904, 1908 Banquet Menus (Oversize Box 1)
  - [1878-1933] Bibliographies of Speeches and Articles by Edwin A. Alderman (Box-folder 11:6)
  - n.d. Biographical Sketch of Edwin A. Alderman by Peyton H. Hoge, a Presbyterian minister (Box-folder 11:7)
  - 1924 Biographical Sketch of Edwin A. Alderman in The National Cyclopedia of American Biography, with correspondence (Box-folder 11:8)
  - [1916 December] Biographical Sketch of Edwin A. Alderman by Lindsay Rogers (Box-folder 11:9)
  - 1909 July Biographical Sketch of Edwin A. Alderman by C. Alphonso Smith (Box-folder 11:10)
  - 1904-1932 Biographical Sketches of Edwin A. Alderman - Miscellaneous authors (Box-folder 11:11)
  - n.d. Bookplates for the Library of Edwin A. Alderman (Box-folder 11:12)
  - 1910-1923 National Civic Federation; National Conference of Charities and Correction; World Court Congress; Win the War for Permanent Peace Convention; and the Centennial Celebration of the Monroe Doctrine; Blank Subscriber to the Thomas Jefferson Memorial Endowment Fund certificate; (Oversize Box 1">Certificates appointing Alderman as a delegate to: National Civic Federation; National Conference of Charities and Correction; World Court Congress; Win the War for Permanent Peace Convention; and the Centennial Celebration of the Monroe Doctrine; Blank Subscriber to the Thomas Jefferson Memorial Endowment Fund certificate; (Oversize Box 1)
  - 1931 May-August Death of Edwin A. Alderman - Alumni News (Box-folder 11:13)
  - 1931 June 13 Death of Edwin A. Alderman - Board of Visitors (Box-folder 11:14)
  - 1931 May 1 Death of Edwin A. Alderman - College Topics (Box-folder 11:15)
  - 1932 Death of Edwin A. Alderman - Commemorative Tribute by John Huston Finley for the American Academy of Arts and Letters; includes invitation to the Memorial Exercises where he delivered the tribute, a proof, and news clippings (Box-folder 11:16)
  - [1931] Death of Edwin A. Alderman - Memorial adopted by the Alumni Board of Trustees, University of Virginia (Box-folder 12:1)
  - 1931-1932 Death of Edwin A. Alderman - Resolutions, Tributes, and Condolences from Groups and Organizations; a typed list of the various groups with the dates of their action can be found in the front of the folder (Box-folder 12:2)
  - 1931 Death of Edwin A. Alderman - Seven Society Message (Box-folder 12:3)
  - 1898 Feb 5-Apr 20 Diary of Edwin A. Alderman's "Journey to the Orient," a cruise including stops in Europe, along the Mediterranean Sea, Egypt, Syria, Palestine, Constantinople, and Greece (Box-folder 12:4)
  - 1900-1916 Financial and Legal Papers (Box-folder 12:5)
  - 1917-1922 Financial and Legal Papers (Box-folder 12:6)
  - 1923-1933 Financial and Legal Papers (Box-folder 12:7)
  - 1919-1920 Financial and Legal Papers - "East Canaan [Account?] Book" recording orders for each Saturday (Box-folder 13:1)
  - 1924 Financial and Legal Papers -Megantic Fish and Game Corporation, [Maine], includes a topographical map of property owned or leased by the corporation, showing trails, ponds, streams and camps (Box-folder 13:2)
  - 1912 Financial and Legal Papers - Last Will and Testament of Edwin A. Alderman (Box-folder 13:3)
  - 1907-1931, n.d. Genealogy of the Alderman Family (Box-folder 13:4)
  - 1899-1912 Honorary degrees awarded to Edwin A. Alderman from Tulane University of Louisiana, Johns Hopkins University, Yale University, Harvard University, and the University of Pennsylvania (Oversize)
  - 1905 Apr 13 Invitations to the Inauguration of Edwin A. Alderman as President of the University of Virginia (Box-folder 13:5)
  - 1904-1929 Invitations - Printed (Box-folder 13:6)
  - 1921, 1929-1931 French Chevalier cross of the Legion of Honor (1929">Medals awarded to Edwin A. Alderman, including: French Chevalier cross of the Legion of Honor (1929); the distinguished cross of Serbia (1921); and Order of Crown of Italy medal (1930); Certificates for medal from Italy and Serbia (re-issued by Yugoslavia in 1931 since it was never received (see letters from Dr. Rosalie Slaughter Morton, January 30, April 6, 1932); certificates in Oversize Box 1
  - 1905-1959, n.d. News clippings, including: dedication of Alderman Library (1938), the publication of Alderman's biography by Dumas Malone (1940), and the death of Bessie Alderman (1959) (Box-folder 13:7)
  - 1928-1929 News clippings concerning the charges made against the University of Virginia by the Reverend David Hepburn, Superintendent of the Virginia Anti-Saloon League, and the response of Alderman in a printed Open Letter to Governor Harry Flood Byrd and prohibition (Box-folder 13:8)
  - 1931-1933 News clippings - concerning the Search to Replace Edwin A. Alderman (Box-folder 13:9)
  - 1897-1926 News clippings concerning Speeches (Box-folder 13:10)
  - 1924 December News clippings concerning the Woodrow Wilson Memorial Address (Box-folder 13:11)
  - 1931 News clippings - Obituaries of Edwin A. Alderman - Charlottesville (Box-folder 13:12)
  - 1931 News clippings - Obituaries of Edwin A. Alderman - Out of State Newspapers (Box-folder 13:13)
  - 1931 News clippings - Obituaries of Edwin A. Alderman - Out of State News clippings - Obituaries of Edwin A. Alderman - Richmond, Virginia Newspapers (Box-folder 14:1)
  - 1931 News clippings - Obituaries of Edwin A. Alderman - Virginia Newspapers (Box-folder 14:2)
  - 1931 News clippings - Obituaries of Edwin A. Alderman - Scrapbook (Box-folder 14:3)
  - 1908 March News clippings - Scrapbook concerning Alderman's Speech "The Growing South," Carnegie Hall, New York City (Box-folder 14:4)
  - 1926 Noell Bill and related papers concerning education, Noell was a member of the Virginia State Senate Committee on Public Institutions and Education (Box-folder 14:5)
  - 1889-1890 North Carolina Board of Education Record Books kept by Alderman as an Institute Conductor and Agent of the Board (Box-folder 14:6)
  - ca. 1917-1918 Notebook kept by Edwin A. Alderman [while on board RMS Adriatic] concerning Woodrow Wilson (Box-folder 14:7)
  - 1897-1926 Passports of Edwin A. Alderman (also two in Oversize Box 1) (Box-folder 14:8)
  - 1904, n.d. Photographs - Bessie Green Hearn Alderman (Box-folder 14:9)
  - 1904, n.d. Photographs - Edwin A. Alderman (Box-folder 14:10)
  - 1881-1904, n.d. Photographs - Edwin A. Alderman as a younger man (Box-folder 14:11)
  - 1930-1931 Photographs - Edwin A. Alderman - bronze bust created by Sergei Konenkov (1874-1971) (Box-folder 14:12)
  - 1916, n.d. Photographs - Edwin A. Alderman - prints and engravings (Box-folder 14:13)
  - n.d. Photographs - Susan Jane Corbett and James Alderman, parents of Edwin A. Alderman (Box-folder 15:1)
  - ca. 1908-1938 Photographs - Events, including Founders Day with Vincent Massey; Alumni gift of a silver service honoring Alderman's 25 th Anniversary with the University; the three Presidents of University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill, Alderman, Harry W. Chase, and Francis P. Venable; dedication of the Woodrow Wilson Memorial Tablet; visit of Ambassador James Bryce, Great Britain, to New York; Alderman standing by the seated statue of Thomas Jefferson; the clock in Alderman Library with dedication "This Building Erected in Memory of Edwin Anderson Alderman First President of the University of Virginia 1904-1931" (Box-folder 15:2)
  - 1921 Photographs - Events - President Alderman and Faculty during the Centennial Celebration of the University of Virginia (Oversize Box 1)
  - 1931 Photographs - Funeral of Edwin A. Alderman (Box-folder 15:3)
  - 1909, n.d. Photographs - Miscellaneous, including: Daniel B. Fayerweather (n.d.); William Howard Taft and Alderman with a Group (1909); a "younger" Alderman at a podium with an unidentified group (n.d.); and a print of the "Last Supper" (n.d.) (Oversize Box 1)
  - 1904-1925 Photographs - Miscellaneous, including: Alderman, Rector and Board of Visitors of the University of Virginia, who elected Alderman as President (1904); Alderman, Rector and Board of Visitors of the University of Virginia, who elected Alderman as President (1904">Photographs - Miscellaneous, including: Alderman, Rector and Board of Visitors of the University of Virginia, who elected Alderman as President (1904); Alderman delivering his Woodrow Wilson Memorial Address before Congress (1924); the Assembly of the League of Nations, Geneva, Switzerland (1925); and a young Alderman with a group of male faculty or teachers in North Carolina (n.d.); (Oversize Box 1)
  - 1903-1921, n.d. Photographs - New Orleans and Unidentified Vacations (Box-folder 15:4)
  - n.d. Photographs - Marcus Cicero Stephens Noble (Box-folder 15:5)
  - 1907-1924 Photographs - University of Virginia (Box-folder 15:6)
  - 1914 Photographs - Vacations - Europe (Box-folder 15:7)
  - 1910-1926 Photographs - Vacations - Maine (Box-folder 15:8)
  - 1907-1928 Photographs - Vacations - New York and Miscellaneous (Box-folder 15:9)
  - 1896-1930, n.d. Printed, including some memorabilia items formerly removed from scrapbooks, such as entrance passes to the Republican and National Progressive Conventions of 1912; entrance passes to the League of Nations meetings; the British Museum Reading Room; and currency; and a speech by Dr. Charles W. Dabney "Summer School Address" (n.d.) (Box-folder 15:10)
  - 1924 Jan 5 Report - "Statistical Survey of Expenditures for Higher Education in Virginia" by Lloyd Morey (Box-folder 15:11)
  - 1893 U.S. Military Academy Board of Visitors Appointment for Edwin A. Alderman (Box-folder 15:12)
  - 1897 January 27 University of North Carolina - Inauguration of Edwin A. Alderman as President (Box-folder 15:13)
  - 1878-1879 University of North Carolina Lectures on Chemistry by Professor Fletcher Redd belonging to Edwin A. Alderman (Box-folder 16:1)
  - 1900 April 7, 17 University of North Carolina Resolutions by Board of Trustees and Faculty requesting Alderman to stay at Chapel Hill (Box-folder 16:2)
  - 1896-1897 University of North Carolina Scrapbook of Clippings "Facts about the University" (Box-folder 16:3)
  - 1921-1923 University of Virginia - Budget Statements (Box-folder 16:4)
  - 1927, 1929, n.d. University of Virginia Calendars (Box-folder 16:5)
  - 1897-1903 University of Virginia - Decision to Select a President to Head the University (Box-folder 16:6)
  - 1914 January University of Virginia - Hearing on Coordination Plan printed in Alumni Bulletin (Box-folder 16:7)
  - 1905 University of Virginia - Installation of Edwin A. Alderman as President (Box-folder 16:8)
  - 1912-1925 University of Virginia - Resolutions by the Rector and Board of Visitors and Others (Box-folder 16:9)
  - 1905-1920 University of Virginia - Statement of Conditions and Needs to the Virginia General Assembly (Box-folder 16:10)
  - 1906-1907 University of Virginia - Statement of Growth (Box-folder 16:11)
  - 1924 Yorktown Country Club, Yorktown, Virginia, Life Membership for Edwin A. Alderman (Box-folder 16:12)
- Series III: Speeches, Addresses, Articles by Alderman
  - 1881 April 27 Speech "Ireland and Her Woes" delivered June 1 as a representative of the Dialectic Society at the University of North Carolina as a junior (Box-folder 17:1)
  - 1882 April 2 Speech -Senior Class Prophecy given at the Senior Class Tree Planting, University of North Carolina (Box-folder 17:2)
  - 1882 May 2 Speech "The Influence of Corporate Power" given at Commencement, the winning speech in the W.P. Magnum Oratory Medal Contest, University of North Carolina (Box-folder 17:3)
  - 1884 June 7 Response to a Toast at the First Reunion and Banquet of Lambda Chapter of the Phi Kappa Sigma Fraternity, Raleigh, North Carolina in Proceedings (print) (Box-folder 17:4)
  - [ca. 1885?] Speech "[Men and Manners in] North Carolina One Hundred years Ago," delivered at the closing exercises of Bethel Academy [1878?], then later at Goldsboro, North Carolina; apparently this speech was given in various forms before dozens of local audiences (Box-folder 17:5)
  - 1886 Lecture "On Teaching History" Black Mountain, [North Carolina Teacher's Convention?] (Box-folder 17:6)
  - 1887 May 30 Memorial Address to the Ladies of the Memorial Association concerning the Confederate Soldier (Box-folder 17:7)
  - 1891 August 6 Article - "A Great Carolinian Archibald D. Murphey, the Father of Our Public Schools," with three letters, 1924-1925, from Alderman and his secretary seeking a printed copy of the article (Box-folder 17:8)
  - 1892 March 7 Article - "The Historic Awakening in N.C.," a news clipping of a speech given by Alderman in Greensboro and bound as small booklet between boards (Box-folder 17:9)
  - 1892 October 15 "An Address Delivered October 15, 1892 by Professor E.A. Alderman at the Guilford Battle Ground on the Occasion of the Dedication of the Monument to the Maryland Soldiers" (print) (Box-folder 17:10)
  - 1894 July 4 Address on the "Life of William Hooper: The Prophet of American Independence," Guilford Battle Ground (print) (Box-folder 17:11)
  - 1894 October Articles "The University Library" and "The University Summer Schools" in the University of North Carolina The Alumni Quarterly Volume I, No. 1 (Box-folder 17:12)
  - 1896 Article "A Brief History of North Carolina" by Edwin A. Alderman (print) (Box-folder 17:13)
  - [ca. 1896-1900] Speech "The State and Education," Durham, North Carolina, manuscripts (Box-folder 17:14)
  - [1897 Apr] Speech on Childhood and the Christian State delivered at the First Presbyterian Church, Wilmington, North Carolina, manuscript (incomplete and fragmentary) (Box-folder 17:15)
  - [1897] September 14 Welcome Address of Alderman to the University of North Carolina Students, notes and news clipping (Box-folder 17:16)
  - [1897?] Speech on Education while at North Carolina (Box-folder 17:17)
  - 1898 January Speech - David Gaston Worth Memorial Service at the University of North Carolina Chapel, printed in The University Record, Chapel Hill (Box-folder 17:18)
  - 1898 February 22 Speech - "Washington and Ideals" delivered on Washington's birthday on board the S.S. Aller, off the island of Malta (Box-folder 17:19)
  - Ca. 1898 Speech Fragments while at North Carolina (Box-folder 17:20)
  - [1898?] Notes on Egypt (Box-folder 17:21)
  - [1890s] Speech dedicating a new High School at High Point, North Carolina - Notes (Box-folder 17:22)
  - 1900 [May 8-11] Speech delivered at the Southern Industrial Convention, Chattanooga, Tennessee, representing Tulane University, includes typescript and notes (Box-folder 17:23)
  - 1900 June [7] Farewell Address at Chapel Hill "The University of Today, Its Work and Needs" published in the North Carolina University Magazine (Box-folder 17:24)
  - 1900 June Article - "Four Things to Do" on Southern Education printed in North Carolina Journal of Education (Box-folder 17:25)
  - 1900 June Commencement Talk to the University of North Carolina Graduating Class (Box-folder 17:26)
  - 1900 [June?] Greetings to the Class of 1900, Tulane University of Louisiana (Box-folder 17:27)
  - 1900 October 15 Opening Address at Tulane University (Box-folder 17:28)
  - 1900 December 6 Speech on Public Education, called "Old Reliable" by Alderman; this version given at Norfolk, chiefly notes (Box-folder 17:29)
  - 1900 Speech "Obligations and Opportunities of Scholarship in the Southern States," also printed in the Proceedings of the National Educational Association (Box-folder 18:1)
  - [1900] Opening Address at Tulane University - Notes for the speech written in pencil on a small pad (Box-folder 18:2)
  - [1900?] Address in New Orleans to a group of businessmen, notes, manuscripts (Box-folder 18:3)
  - 1901 March 12 Inaugural Address by Edwin Anderson Alderman on Installation as President of Tulane University, Louisiana (print) (Box-folder 18:4)
  - [1901 April 25] Speech on childhood [possibly a draft of "The Child and the State"?] delivered at a Conference in Athens, Georgia, and published in the Proceedings 5 th Conference for Education in South, pages 55-62 (Box-folder 18:5)
  - 1901 [May?] Speech concerning the organization of Tulane University (Box-folder 18:6)
  - [ca. 1901 June ?] Talk delivered at Tulane Night at the Theater "at the raising of the curtain" (Box-folder 18:7)
  - 1901 August 3 Article - "Education in the South" in Outlook, Volume 68, No. 14, pages 775-780 (print) (Box-folder 18:8)
  - [1901 Fall] Address to the Tulane University Students, typescript (Box-folder 18:9)
  - 1901 November 7 Notes for [Waldorf Speech?], manuscript (Box-folder 18:10)
  - 1901 Speech on College Reading delivered to students at Tulane University (Box-folder 18:11)
  - [1901?] Manuscript - "Some Principles in Curry's Educational Theory, as frequently expressed in his speeches and writings" (Box-folder 18:12)
  - 1902 February 14 Notes for "The Modern City" (Box-folder 18:13)
  - 1902 February 22 Speech - Johns Hopkins Economic Association - Notes (Box-folder 18:14)